Toor shul! {"Inferno Sun"}
            
            
        Vol toor shul! {"Horror Inferno Sun"}
            
            
        Dovahkiin! No!!
            
            
        Lingrah krosis saraan Strundu'ul, voth nid balaan klov praan nau. Naal Thu'umu, mu ofan nii nu, Dovahkiin, naal suleyk do Kaan, naal suleyk do Shor, ahrk naal suleyk do Atmorasewuth. Meyz nu Ysmir, Dovahsebrom. Dahmaan daar rok.
            
            
        Sahloknir! Ziil gro dovah ulse! Slen Tiid Vo!
            
            
        Alduin, thuri! Boaan tiid vokriiha suleysksejun kruziik?
            
            
        Geh, Sahloknir, kaali mir.
            
            
        Ful, losei Dovahkiin? Zu'u koraav nid nol dov do hi. You do not even know our tongue, do you? Such arrogance, to dare take for yourself the name of Dovah. Sahloknir, krii daar joorre.
            
            
        I am Sahloknir! Hear my Voice and despair!
            
            
        Dovahkiin, your Voice is no match for mine!
            
            
        Drem Yo Lok. Greetings, wunduniik. I am Paarthurnax. Who are you? What brings you to my strunmah...my mountain?
            
            
        I am as my father Akatosh made me. As are you...Dovahkiin.
            
            
        They see me as master. Wuth. Onik. Old and wise. It is true I am old...
            
            
        Yes. Vahzah. You speak true, Dovahkiin. Forgive me. It has been long since I last tinvaak with a stranger. I gave in to the temptation to prolong our speech.
            
            
        Evenaar bahlok. There are many hungers it is better to deny than to feed. Dreh ni nahkip. Discipline against the lesser aids in qahnaar...denial of the greater.
            
            
        Tell me. Why do you come here, volaan? Why do you intrude on my meditation?
            
            
        Drem. Patience. There are formalities which must be observed, at the first meeting of two of the dov. By long tradition, the elder speaks first. Hear my Thu'um! Feel it in your bones! Match it, if you are Dovahkiin! Yol...Toor...Shul!
            
            
        The Word calls you. Go to it.
            
            
        A gift, Dovahkiin. Yol. Understand Fire as the dov do.
            
            
        Now, show me what you can do. Greet me not as mortal, but as dovah! Do not be afraid. Faasnu. Let me feel the power of your Thu'um.
            
            
        Aaah...yes! Sossedov los mul. The dragonblood runs strong in you. It is long since I had the pleasure of speech with one of my own kind. So. You have made your way here, to me. No easy task for a joor...mortal. Even for one of Dovah Sos. Dragonblood. What would you ask of me?
            
            
        Ah. I have expected you. Prodah. You would not come all this way for tinvaak with an old dovah. No. You seek your weapon against Alduin.
            
            
        Alduin komeyt tiid. What else would you seek? Alduin and Dovahkiin return together. But, I do not know the Thu'um you seek. Krosis.
            
            
        Hmm. Yes. They are very protective of me. Bahlaan fahdonne. But I do not know the Thu'um you seek. Krosis.
            
            
        Krosis. Sorrowfully, no.
            
            
        It cannot be known to me. Your kind -- joorre -- mortals -- created it as a weapon against the dov...the dragons. Our hadrimme, our minds cannot even...comprehend its concepts.
            
            
        Drem. All in good time. First, a question for you. Why do you want to learn this Thu'um?
            
            
        Nid. If you wish me to answer your question, you must answer mine.
            
            
        Yes. Alduin...zeymah. The elder brother. Gifted, grasping and troublesome as is so often the case with firstborn. But why? Why must you stop Alduin?
            
            
        True... But qostiid -- prophecy -- tells what may be, not what should be. Qostiid sahlo aak. Just because you can do a thing, does not always mean you should. Do you have no better reason for acting than destiny? Are you nothing but a plaything of dez...of fate?
            
            
        Pruzah. As good a reason as any. There are many who feel as you do, although not all. Some would say that all things must end, so that the next can come to pass. Perhaps this world is simply the Egg for the next kalpa? Lein vokiin? Would you stop the next world from being born?
            
            
        Hahaha! You have much to learn of the dov, then. There is nothing else but philosophy to a dovah. It is no accident that we do battle with our Thu'um, our Voices. There is no distinction between debate and combat to a dragon. Tinvaak los grah. For us it is one and the same.
            
            
        Paaz. A fair answer. Ro fus...maybe you only balance the forces at work to quicken the end of this world. Even we who ride the currents of Time cannot see past Time's end. Wuldsetiid los tahrodiis. Those who try to hasten the end, may delay it. Those who work to delay the end, may bring it closer.
            
            
        And so, perhaps, your destiny will be fulfilled. Who can say? Dez motmahus. Even to the dov, who ride the currents of Time, destiny is elusive. Alduin believes that he will prevail, with good reason. Rok mul. And he is no fool. Ni mey, rinik gut nol. Far from it. He began as the wisest and most far-seeing of us all.
            
            
        But you have indulged my weakness for speech long enough. Krosis. Now I will answer your question. Do you know why I live here, at the peak o the Monahven -- what you name Throat of the World?
            
            
        True. But few now remember that this was the very spot where Alduin was defeated by the ancient Tongues. Vahrukt unslaad... perhaps none but me now remember how he was defeated.
            
            
        This is the most sacred mountain in Skyrim. Zok revak strunmah. The great mountain of the world. Here the ancient Tongues, the first mortal masters of the Voice, brought Alduin to battle and defeated him.
            
            
        Drem. Patience. I am answering, in my way. This is the most sacred mountain in Skyrim. Zok revak strunmah. The great mountain of the world. Here the ancient Tongues, the first mortal masters of the Voice, brought Alduin to battle and defeated him.
            
            
        Yes and no. Viik nuz ni kron. Alduin was not truly defeated, either. If he was, you would not be here today, seeking to... defeat him. The Nords of those days used the Dragonrend Shout to cripple Alduin. But this was not enough. Ok mulaag unslaad. It was the Kel -- the Elder Scroll. They used it to...cast him adrift on the currents of Time.
            
            
        Hmm. How to explain in your tongue? The dov have words for such thing that joorre do not. It is an...artifact from outside time. It does not exist, but it has always existed. Rah wahlaan. They are...hmm...fragments of creation. The Kelle...Elder Scrolls, as you name them, they have often been used for prophecy. Yes, your prophecy comes from an Elder Scroll. But this is only a small part of their power. Zofaas suleyk.
            
            
        Not intentionally. Some hoped he would be gone forever, forever lost. Meyye. I knew better. Tiid bo amativ. Time flows ever onward. One day he would surface. Which is why I have lived here. For thousands of mortal years I have waited. I knew where he would emerge but not when.
            
            
        Tiid krent. Time was...shattered here because of what the ancient Nords did to Alduin. If you brought that Kel, that Elder Scroll back here...to the Tiid-Ahraan, the Time-Wound... With the Elder Scroll that was used to break Time, you may be able to...cast yourself back. To the other end of the break. You could learn Dragonrend from those who created it.
            
            
        Krosis. No. I know little of what has passed below in the long years I have lived here. You are likely better informed than I.
            
            
        Trust your instincts, Dovahkiin. Your blood will show you the way.
            
            
        Return it here, to the Tiid-Ahraan. Then... Kelle vomindok. Nothing is certain with such things. But I believe the Scroll's bond with the Tiid-Ahraan will allow you a...a seeing, a vision of the moment of its creation. Then you will feel -- know -- Dragonrend, in the power of its first expression. You will see them...wuth fadonne...my friends -- Hakon, Gormlaith, Felldir.
            
            
        The first mortals that I taught the Thu'um -- the first Tongues. The leaders of the rebellion against Alduin. They were mighty, in their day. Even to attempt to defeat Alduin...sahrot hunne. The Nords have had many heroes since, but none greater.
            
            
        Vomindok. I do not know. Perhaps in the very doing they erased the knowing of it from Time itself. The dov are children of Akatosh. Thus we are specially...attuned to the flow of Time. Perhaps also uniquely vulnerable. I warned them against such a rash action. Even I could not foresee its consequences. Nust ni hon. They would not listen.
            
            
        Yes. There were a few of us that rebelled against Alduin's thur... his tyranny. We aided the humans in his overthrow. But they did not trust us. Ni ov. Their inner councils were kept hidden from us. I was far from here on the day of Alduin's downfall. But all dov felt the...sundering of Time itself.
            
            
        I cannot tell you in detail. I never heard it used. Kogaan. It was the first Thu'um created solely by mortals. It was said to force a dragon to experience the concept of Mortality. A truly vonmindoraan...incomprehensible idea to the immortal dov.
            
            
        You have it. The Kel -- the Elder Scroll. Tiid kreh...qalos. Time shudders at its touch. There is no question. You are doom-driven. Kogaan Akatosh. The very bones of the earth are at your disposal. Go then. Fulfill your destiny. Take the Scroll to the Time-Wound. Do not delay. Alduin will be coming. He cannot miss the signs.
            
            
        Meyye! Tahrodiis aanne! Him hinde pah liiv! Zu'u hin daan!
            
            
        Nivahriin joorre! What have you done? What twisted Words have you created?! Tahrodiis Paarthurnax! My teeth to his neck! But first...dir ko maar. You will die in terror, knowing your final fate... To feed my power when I come for you in Sovngarde!
            
            
        Faal Kel...?! Niikriinne...
            
            
        Bahloki nahkip sillesejoor. My belly is full of the souls of your fellow mortals, Dovahkiin. Die now and await your fate in Sovngarde!
            
            
        Lost funt. You are too late, Alduin! 
            
            
        Suleyki mulaag, Paarthurnax. My power has waxed, while yours has waned.
            
            
        Dovahkiin! Use Dragonrend, if you know it!
            
            
        Unslaad hakoron! Never again!
            
            
        You will pay for your defiance!
            
            
        This is your chance, Dovahkiin! Strike with all your force!
            
            
        You may have picked up the weapons of my ancient foe, but you are not their equal!
            
            
        Dovahkiin, vosaraan! Use Dragonrend before Alduin consumes you!
            
            
        Meyz mul, Dovahkiin. You have become strong. But I am Al-du-in, firstborn of Akatosh! Mulaagi zok lot! I cannot be slain here, by you or anyone else! You cannot prevail against me. I will outlast you... mortal!
            
            
        Lot krongrah. You truly have the Voice of a dovah. Alduin's allies will think twice after this victory.
            
            
        Ni liivrah hin moro. True, this is not the final krongrah -- victory. But not even the heroes of old were able to defeat Alduin in open battle. Alduin always was pahlok -- arrogant in his power. Uznahgar paar. He took domination as his birthright. This should shake the loyalty of the dov who serve him.
            
            
        Hmm, yes. But your su'um is strong. I do not doubt that you can convince him of the need.
            
            
        Yes. This was ages ago, you understand. There were more of us then. Before the bruniikke -- the Akaviri -- came and killed all my zeymah. I used to visit him from time to time. Nearly crazed by loneliness and captivity. Tiiraz sivaas. He did not even remember his own name. I do not know how he came to be caught. But the bronjun...the Jarl...was very proud of his pet. Paak! The hofkahsejun has been known as Dragonsreach ever since.
            
            
        I have taught the Way of the Voice for centuries and the Thu'um since long before that. But no, Dovahkiin. Others do not come here to train anymore. Saraan. You are the first in over a hundred years. I meditate on the Rotmulaag -- the Words of Power. I counsel in their use. It is enough for me.
            
            
        Knowing a Word of Power is to take its meaning into yourself. Contemplate the meaning of a Rotmulaag. You will become closer to that Word, as it fills your inner self. Will I teach you, Dovahkiin? What Word calls you to deeper understanding? There are three to master: Fus, Feim, and Yol.
            
            
        It is called "Force" in your tongue. But as you push the world, so does the world push back. Think of the way force may be applied effortlessly. Imagine but a whisper pushing aside all in its path. That is "Fus." Let its meaning fill you. Su'um ahrk morah. You will push the world harder than it pushes back.
            
            
        "Fade" in your tongue. Mortals have greater affinity for this word than the dov. Everything mortal fades away in time, but the spirit remains. Ponder the meaning of spirit. Unslaad zii. Where mortal flesh may wither and die, the spirit endures. That is "Feim." Let that meaning fill you. Su'um ahrk morah. You will find that your spirit will give you more strength.
            
            
        In your tongue, the Word simply means "fire." It is change given form. Power at its most primal. That is the true meaning of "Yol." Suleyk. Power. You have it, as do all dov. But power is inert without action and choice. Think of this as the fire builds in your su'um, in your breath. Su'um ahrk morah. What will you burn? What will you spare?
            
            
        Hmm, yes. I have been pondering on exactly that question. Lingrah morah. I have tasted the voices of Alduin's allies on the wind. Pogaan nahlaas, vokrii wah jun. There is one who I remember well. Odahviing. He is the one to tell us where Alduin has gone.
            
            
        Ah, I forget how little you know of the dov. Our names are always made of us three Rotmulaag -- Words of Power. You see -- Paar-thur-nax -- a Thu'um -- a Shout, yes?
            
            
        He is not compelled to come, but the dov are prideful by nature. Few could resist such a challenge. Especially from you, Dovahkiin. But Odahviing, he is...headstrong? Boziik. Rash. Even among the dov, he was known for this. He will not resist the challenge of your Voice, Dovahkiin. He will come. Now -- hear his name. Odahviing. Taste it on the wind. Od-ah-viing. Know it in your su'um. Od-ah-viing!
            
            
        Dovahkiin! Here I am!
            
            
        Ni fas, Dovahkiin!
            
            
        Nid!
            
            
        Horvutah med kodnaav. Caught like a bear in a trap... Zok frini grind ko grah drun viiki, Dovahkiin. Ah. I forget. You do not have the dovah speech. My...eagerness to meet you in battle was my... undoing. Dovahkiin. I salute your, hmm...low cunning in devising such a grahmindol -- strategem. Zu'u bonaar. You went to a great deal of trouble to put me in this...humiliating position. Hind siiv Alduin, hmm? No doubt you want to know where to find Alduin?
            
            
        Rinik vazah. An apt phrase. Alduin bovul. One reason I came to your call was to test your Thu'um for myself. Many of us have begun to question Alduin's lordship, whether his Thu'um is truly the strongest. Among ourselves, of course. Mu ni meyye. None were yet ready to openly defy him.
            
            
        Unslaad krosis. Innumerable pardons. I digress. He has travelled to Sovngarde to regain his strength, devouring the sillesejoor...the souls of the mortal dead. A privilege he jealously guards... His door to Sovngarde is at Skuldafn, one of his ancient fanes high in the eastern mountains. Mindoraan, pah ok middovahhe lahvraan til. I surely do not need to warn you that all his remaining strength is marshalled there. Zu'u lost ofan hin laan...now that I have answered your question, you will allow me to go free?
            
            
        Aam? Serve you? ...no. Ni tiid. If and when you defeat Alduin, I will reconsider.
            
            
        Ah. Well. Hmm...krosis. There is one...detail about Skuldafn I neglected to mention.
            
            
        Only this. You have the Thu'um of a dovah, but without the wings of one, you will never set foot in Skuldafn. Of course...I could fly you there. But not while imprisoned like this.
            
            
        Indeed. Orin brit ro. I cannot leave here until you defeat Alduin, which you cannot do without my help.
            
            
        Ahraan. You wound me, Dovahkiin. I may not tell the whole truth, but I am no liar. Go and see for yourself. Zu'u ni bo nol het. I will be here...unless Alduin returns before you do.
            
            
        Onikraan koraav gein miraad. It is wise to recognize when you only have one choice. And you can trust me. Zu'u ni tahrodiis. Alduin has proven himself unworthy to rule. I go my own way now. Free me, and I will carry you to Skuldafn.
            
            
        Begone, mage. Do not test my promise to the Dovahkiin.
            
            
        Joor mey! What are you doing back there? Yol...Toor...Shul!
            
            
        The Blades are wise not to trust me. Onikaan ni ov. I would not trust another dovah.
            
            
        Dov wahlaan fah rel. We were made to dominate. The will to power is in our blood. You feel it in yourself, do you not? I can be trusted. I know this. But they do not. Onikaan ni ov dovah. It is always wise to mistrust a dovah. I have overcome my nature only through meditation and long study of the Way of the Voice. No day goes by where I am not tempted to return to my inborn nature. Zin krif horvut se suleyk. What is better -- to be born good, or to overcome your evil nature through great effort? 
            
            
        Faas nu, zint dein ruthi ahst vaal.
            
            
        Saraan uth -- I await your command, as promised. Are you ready to see the world as only a dovah can?
            
            
        This is far as I can take you. Krif voth ahkrin. I will look for your return, or Alduin's.
            
            
        Ven Mul Riik!
            
            
        Ven Mul Riik!
            
            
        Nust wo ni qilaan fen kos duuan.
            
            
        You are persistent, Dovahkiin. Pruzeh ol aar. A fine slave you would have made.
            
            
        Zu'u unslaad! zu'u nis oblaan!
            
            
        So, it is done. Alduin dilon. The Eldest is no more, he who came before all others, and has always been.
            
            
        Many of the dovahhe are now scattered across Keizaal. Without Alduin's lordship, they may yet bow to the vahzen...rightness of my Thu'um. But willing or no, they will hear it! Fare thee well, Dovahkiin!
            
            
        Pruzah wundunne wah Wuth Gein. I wish the old one luck in his... quest. But I doubt many will wish to exchange Alduin's lordship for the tyranny of Paarthurnax's "Way of the Voice". As for myself, you've proven your mastery twice over. Thuri, Dovahkiin. I gladly acknowledge the power of your Thu'um. Zu'u Odahviing. Call me when you have need, and I will come if I can.
            
            
        Stay your weapons. I would speak with you, Qahnaarin.
            
            
        Cursed, not dead. Doomed to exist in this form for all eternity. Trapped between laas and dinok, between life and death.
            
            
        I believe in civility among seasoned warriors, and I find your ear worthy of my words. My claws have rended flesh from innumerable foes, but I have never once been felled on the field of battle. I therefore honor-name you "Qahnaarin," or Vanquisher in your tongue.
            
            
        Your words do me great honor. My desire to speak with you was born from the result of our battle, Qahnaarin. I merely wish to respectfully ask a favor of you.
            
            
        The hostility was necessary. I was bound to an oath.
            
            
        Forgive me, Qahnaarin. We will continue this when time releases you from its relentless grasp.
            
            
        For countless years I've roamed the Soul Cairn, in unintended service to the Ideal Masters. Before this, I roamed the skies above Tamriel. I desire to return there.
            
            
        I fear that my time here has taken its toll on me. I share a bond with this dreaded place. If I ventured far from the Soul Cairn, my strength would begin to wane until I was no more.
            
            
        I will place my name with you and grant you the right to call my name from Tamriel. Do me this simple honor and I will fight at your side as your Grah-Zeymahzin, your Ally, and teach you my Thu'um.
            
            
        Trivial in your mind, perhaps. For me, it would mean a great deal. I don't require an answer, Qahnaarin. Simply speak my name to the heavens when you feel the time is right.
            
            
        In my language, the Qahnaarin is the Vanquisher, the one who has bested a fellow dovah in battle.
            
            
        Forgive me, my instinct was to grant you this title. I am uncertain why. Perhaps one day it will become clear to both of us.
            
            
        There was a time when I called Tamriel my home, but those days have long since passed. The dovah roamed the skies, vying for their small slices of territory that resulted in immense and ultimately fatal battles.
            
            
        I was. But unlike some of my brethren, I sought solutions outside the norm in order to maintain my superiority. I began to explore what the dovah call "Alok-Dilon," the ancient forbidden art that you call necromancy.
            
            
        The Ideal Masters assured me that my powers would be unmatched, that I could raise legions of the undead. In return, I was to serve them as a Keeper until the death of the one who calls herself Valerica.
            
            
        I discovered too late that the Ideal Masters favor deception over honor and had no intention of releasing me from my binding. They had control of my mind, but fortunately they couldn't possess my soul.
            
            
        Free? No. I've been here too long, Qahnaarin. The Soul Cairn has become a part of what I am. I can never fully call Tamriel my home again, or I would surely perish. I only hope that you will allow me the precious moments of time there through your call.
            
            
        The time comes soon when... What?
            
            
        Who are you to dare set foot here? Ah... You are Dragonborn. I can feel it. And yet... You have done little beyond killing a few dragons. You have no idea of the true power a Dragonborn can wield! Mul...Qah Diiv! This realm is beyond you. You have no power here. And it is only a matter of time before Solstheim is also mine. I already control the minds of its people. Soon they will finish building my temple, and I can return home. She can await my arrival with the rest of Tamriel.
            
            
        This dragon's soul belongs to me. One step closer to my return.
            
            
        Hail, thuri. Your thu'um has the mastery. Climb aboard and I will carry you to Miraak.
            
            
        Beware. Miraak is strong. He knew you would come here.
            
            
        Sahrotaar, are you so easily swayed?
            
            
        No. Not yet. We should greet our guest first. And so the First Dragonborn meets the Last Dragonborn at the summit of Apocrypha. No doubt just as Hermaeus Mora intended. He is a fickle master, you know. But now I will be free of him. My time in Apocrypha is over. You are here in your full power, and thus subject to my full power. You will die. And with the power of your soul, I will return to Solstheim and be master of my own fate once again. Kruziikrel! Relonikiv! Now!
            
            
        So easily you betray me, after all these years.
            
            
        Kruziikrel, ziil los dii du!
            
            
        Relonikiv, ziil los dii du!
            
            
        Fate decreed that you had to die so that I could win my freedom.
            
            
        Sahrotaar, ziil los dii du!
            
            
        May he be rewarded for her service as I am!
            
            
        